uh first of all the second time has been
decided to be Fridays uh 10 30 a.m in
the same room here
um and uh we understand that uh from the
poll that's not exactly everyone can can
make it but we'll report it and uh uh
and also Alex will go to the office hour
afterwards at two to three p.m on
Fridays uh in uh Jefferson 453 the seven
room upstairs
further questions after the section if
you go uh Billy's office hour
um and um uh the first uh problem set
has been posted is in the homework
Channel um slack
um uh you know you don't need to look at
now in fact some of the stuff will make
more sense after today's lecture
um I should say that uh the problems uh
look pretty long but it was mostly the
statement that try to guide you through
the problems so it's actually a lot
longer the better because
taking out the convention and explain
what you need to do
um and um you know if you if you happen
to be if event is scary and they don't
know what to do it shouldn't worry
um you know we're here to to help you to
guide you through this you know once you
understand the physics the actual
problems are actually pretty trivial um
like 90 of doing physics is to
understand how is that the calculation
you know and most of the time once you
understand exactly what they do the
actual calculation is pretty easy at
least the not the way that these
problems don't do that uh so so don't be
scared but I do uh encourage you to look
at it right away after the class
um don't wait till last minute
also it's due on Tuesday
um the reason uh usually you won't make
it bi-weekly but uh this problem said is
actually despite the land of the
statements actually on the shorter side
so so we want to make it do you want you
on Tuesday
um and uh uh but you know as I said
don't come with your last week yes
the text source for the Primitive yeah
uh uh sure uh do you prefer looking in
the attack than PDF
so we can like fight the solutions uh oh
uh uh sure but but yeah
but the other thing everyone use paper
snack for us it's not exactly the same
time
maybe not inconvenient but anyway I I
can see
okay
so uh
um so so let's start with uh uh with the
physics
um so last time I uh introduced the time
in the world people can find the
mechanics
um and um now I'm going to discuss uh
how you would use this probabilism to
study some observables uh that uh
captures uh you know physical quantities
of Interest such as the energy spectrum
of a quantum mechanical system
um so um
we were considering it's on a simple
funding mechanical models with uh
finding many degrees freedom to begin
with with some hamiltonian operator uh
but sometimes you're telling me as a
function that uh uh
[Music]
um so
um
say we're interested in
um the uh energy levels of the
hamiltonian
um I'm gonna probe that by studying the
following quantity
performance
um so uh basically
um uh observable uh of Interest which
will be uh particularly convenient upon
the filter even though this is not
something that's often always discussing
quantum mechanics uh
um is uh
correlation uh functions
uh in the ground state because
um so it might be a kind of a peculiar
thing because that's it everybody you'll
see it's already why it's a natural
thing to do study the ground state are
denoted by zero gets pronounced
um
um later uh it should be clear depending
on whether I write Q if I write Q as an
operator acting on the states sometimes
I will drop the hat or forget to write
the Hat it should be clear depending on
the context whether it's an operator or
a uh is a bear so so now it's operator
you have uh uh now uh as uh We've
written in the last lecture
um this Q has update uh the timely
Evolution dictated by this
um
uh relation uh into that I over R which
has B into that minus the signal Base
Bar which had a t that's how the
operator evolved in either a picture uh
so the query function I'm going to be
interested in is the following you've
had a uh you had zero uh in the vacuum
and take its overlap with the value so
this thing uh because it's the two-point
equation function in in the ground state
um others so G of B
right so that's the definition
uh any questions so far
and so so there's a definition so I
think you had the time zero average if
you had the time T again the things
overlap with the vacuum notation always
actually is in a hydrogen break picture
so you know the the say does not involve
um
okay
now uh why would we care about Central
quantity
uh well uh obviously uh if you have a
question
um so if you have a uh what's a normal
basis
of energy
uh
and say
um
this person said and in some en ends of
the answer to that
and so forth
um then uh we can write this G of D so
we can insert a complete basis
so basis
uh
United States
um is there a complete basis in uh here
uh and uh equivalently right there's two
point for your function as the sun over
energy
and yes zero
foreign
[Music]
so
if it's okay is then not equal to sum
over n
and zero or two times zero and and uh
zero zero sometimes the
foreign
[Music]
any questions
um okay so this is going to be a basic
Observer of interest because
um you see it captured the energy level
so it has a difference between the
energy of the ground state and any
exciting State uh in principle if you
know GOP is the function P you can do
the inverse polio transform and figure
out so captured all the information the
product is that this overlap is not zero
which genetically would be
um now of course if you take the
harmonic oscillator there's an accident
if you take a common alternator actually
this state only is non-trivial for n
equals one but but the more generic
system this Q had on the vacuum I can
come across that it will generally have
none zero overlap with any excited
States in that situation there's um two
point function will capture all the
energy Spectrum Within
okay so so that's one reason why I would
be interested in this but another reason
I do speak swirly is that this is
something that's uh relatively easy to
calculate using the pattern more
formative
um so uh my assumption
uh e n minus e0
is uh is not negative because we're
assuming the easier always
um so
uh
uh one of the things we're going to do
with this with something we're going to
be doing all the time in common field
Theory uh is to real tree of e not just
as function of a real number T but I'm
going to consider it as an energy
function in C and another continue G of
T so complex values of d
okay so uh by the way uh how many people
feel comfortable with the notion of
another continuation of analytic
function okay I think not everybody
because um uh now uh don't worry you
know we will uh introduce these things
gently uh but um uh I should say that uh
the first thing or most important
mathematical tool for Quantum field
theory is complex analysis in one
variable so this is something that uh if
you're not familiar with at this point
you will be familiar with by the Android
so so we'll
we'll
be you know introducing things uh as we
go along
um uh but uh but now this is the first
time we're gonna encounter that so
um
but let me make a statement
um so
uh imagine you uh I'll take this pumpkin
gft and extend the notion so April is
defined for real number T real-time
Devolution uh but we're gonna imagine uh
we're gonna attempt to try to extend GOP
uh as a function uh complex by the
function of complex primary 13. now can
we actually do that
uh now if you look at the sum in terms
by term obviously you can do that
because you have this exponential you
can replace the T from a real number to
a complex number there's nothing wrong
about that
um but there's a question that when the
sun will converge
uh the sound generated infinite sum
there's a question of whether converges
um typically a quantity system you can
take the harmonic oscillator but how
many ounces actually is maybe it's too
trivial for this purpose because 10 is
actually equal to one of the sum from
case but for generic uh you know uh
system with some arbitrary then one
degree level arbitrary potential let's
say
um the sound could be evidence sound but
in that situation uh you have to be a
little hair because uh if you replace
this T by compact parameter depending on
the sign of this imaginary part uh you
know if you want to have an I uh the I
times T will have a real power it can
take the positive sign or negative sign
so generally if you take if the sign if
minus i t has positive real part then
they multiply this energy this will grow
exponentially for higher difference and
then typically the sum might uh diverge
and this result is it'll be fine it will
not exist
um on the other hand if you um
uh so if you analytically
continue
um
uh to uh complexity
uh well
uh imaginary party Limited
then you have a minus I absolutely
positive and then R minus I again so you
have the real part of this exponent will
be some negative number times UI minus
e0 that'll be as long as you're
suppressed by high energy
so in that case the sum will tend to
converge and indeed there's a
mathematical theorem so which I'll now
elaborate here
um that will guarantee
um that this sum provide that makes
sense the real key is going to make
sense also at reminder P the Omega
uh in which case
um so uh
for this the sum of N converges
um and uh P of T is a qualifying
um and uh has some nice properties which
I will not fully elaborate on but uh to
say that it is
this this continuation uh through
complex by their p is well defined uh a
pro I provide you that imagine part of
these
okay so we're going to be interested in
studying this two-point magnitude of Aid
not only for real T but for
um uh complexity with negative imaginary
parts
a few squares so effectively to be what
zero is
fine no not necessarily uh oh
and gm0 is fine but that's not the what
I'm worried about I'm worried about uh
um uh I'm worried about uh uh you know
acquiring a positive imagine Fund in
that case sure
uh no uh so far I haven't made any
additional statement right all I'm
saying is that let's go into contact
but here it's a real axis this is the
imaginary axis
um uh so uh all we say is that so
abrahim's achieved they find anywhere
around that because it relaxes uh and I
can't I think go down and um and I
expect that
cool
um okay
if you know what happens to the
imaginary team
oh yes absolutely
um uh so uh well that that's the thing
that uh about any continuation uh
perhaps yeah uh let me say a few more
words about about uh growth emergency
and I'll come back to
come back to the extent to which uh you
can determinate this
um so uh in particularly important case
uh is uh
um
so
for example uh let's take C to be minus
I now where now is a positive real
number
called the real number
um and uh commonly you know this is
sometimes called the weak rotation
um I don't like this term rotation
because uh it's not really we're not
relatively anything it's really any
configuration and you know this will
become clear uh into examples
um but um
in this case
if we start with this this guy uh but we
think T to B minus right now
um uh well
down there of course so so here we have
a sum over n
zero two zero and and
two zero zero this is just one number
and now and e to the minus one over H
bar the N minus e0
as I said earlier you know these things
are explodingly suppressed at higher
energies and there's some typically
convergence
um and uh it is also going to be true
that uh if you uh know the value of the
GRT on the negative axis
um you can uh if you also know that it's
analytic in parallel you can uh
unambiguously can view this back to real
um
uh
uh to agree about your teeth uh maybe
just as a as as a a kind of a brief
mathematical aside how does this work in
general you have some function update uh
that uh a functional real value how does
that conversion work uh I'll just make a
quick comment about that so um so again
imagine trying to define the function on
the complex deep plane with the real
axis here and imagine access over there
so a plus RI this function would be
defined anywhere along the real axis
uh now uh uh suppose the function is
analytic at one point which means that
the Taylor series of the function
converted to the function itself in a
neighborhood of that point uh so over
here you can write the paper series
sum over a and t minus d0 relative and
where this point is the mineral
get suppressed by some um some number to
Npower uh this uh uh these uh every term
in the sum well because of the sum will
converge we'll have some radius
comparatives let's say let's say this
this is the radius convergence
um and uh converters
um it always will also converge if you
replace uh T minus t 0 it will replace d
uh by not just any real number on this
interval but by the compass number in
this little disk so so the the
stereotypes will Converge on this disk
so we Define anywhere inside of this as
an under function
um and uh so that defines unambiguously
the element integration the function
from this part of the real interval to
the disk from complex play but you don't
stop there uh you can now start uh a new
from any point into this and ask uh what
if you do data expansion over here and
they might have some other radius
converters maybe convergence and the
start of a point over here maybe
conversion that is and so on and so
forth and uh in this way uh the the
value of the function on this interval
of the real line will determine is the
value on the sequence of this into the
complex aspect this is how integration
works right sometimes uh this might be
obstructive if you discover that your
strong Singularity of the function on
the complex plane you can have the
failure series but not the radius
convergence cannot extend beyond the
points
um so that there could become
obstruction but in absence of custom
fractions you can new by this sequence
of the disks and do the Taylor expansion
over this sequence events so
um I mean you know if you're not I mean
I witness um
okay uh but this is another procedure
that allows you to define the
information and despite the structure
Analytics
uh any questions
yeah
I this is the definition of
beneficiation
I'm saying that I sort of function with
reality I can associate and move the
function of one context here
uh and let me repeat what I said here uh
the way this functional complex variable
is constructed by taking the pillar
Series right so starting with 10
receivers around a point on the real
axis I can any random data series which
we tend to find their way to convert so
if you have to find the radius
convergence it will also converge you
can replace B by a complex number inside
this list
um and therefore
inside the disk uh this produces a
complex analytic function that is
defined on this
as well defined under this one is going
to start at the another point on this
and do the same procedure uh provided
that uh that you still have some radius
number
uh you know I I invite you to
and I'll try the example of uh like
one over one minus D over something that
is yeah
if you take the the function the one
over a common is e right they start at
the origin you'll find that there's
already convergence which is equality
over here but so if you if you just do
the Taylor series uh you're stuck on
this disk but if you really expand over
here you can go around this and and you
know so by by this procedure you can
cover the python explain exceptions so
this is how it works
okay uh any other questions
yeah
actually yeah when you're you're in the
initial Circle in front of an area
Circle are you using the same particular
Series
yeah because I'm really expanding the
function uh at that point and so I need
to use the average derivative of in
order to function at that point
anyway
so it's all additional questions will be
we'll go into the section
uh I I will not use that if I but
anything I will actually use I will um
you know I will explain more but for now
uh I think we we know we need to proceed
uh
okay
um
um all right so
uh uh your sister review that why this
will be a convenient thing to do
um
so um we assume that there's a gap
uh due to the first excited state and
the ground state I suppose the energy
between U1 is zero uh is impossible so
there's no regeners here they run a
scale uh in that situation
uh we can we can replace
uh
this zero cat in this polarity function
uh by wow uh you know and basically it's
an arbitrary generic state it doesn't at
the beginning
uh and uh let me consider the
um well we'll consider the operator
imagine time uh let me take uh is the
minus one of H bar uh H minus B naught
of t
uh and I take a limit
ation
so this is a procedure that uh looks
like kind of find the evolution of the
state in imaginary time uh and as an
inner limit as an imaginary time to
to Infinity uh this operator is going to
kill everything by the ground state
everything that's not right will be
supporting suppressed
so absolute organization if you pick
some generic status overlap with the
ground state so this limit is going to
pick up pick up address the ground state
component
s
um
so
um so the acquiring function largely in
the ground states of Interest I can do a
bit of rewriting so this uh 2.200
function you've had d q 0 is 0. uh how
can I do this way so this is the same as
the limits of capital and Divinity of
the following I think some objects to
say PSI
um
over here
I do this which is e to the minus 1 over
is bar 100 million times P because
sometimes I forget to write a hat
uh this matter so you should always have
a hat on it into the
on the right bar
okay this is the original concrete of
that
uh and uh QT
q0
um and uh a normalize this by
by the thing without the query circuits
onto the minus two over this bar
the time
uh as you can see this is uh this is
equal to that because what I found right
hand side is uh simply to pick out the
contribution uh from the ground state
components of uh of the state side and
this uh minus e0 here doesn't matter
because it's going to cancel between the
numerator
in fact I think last lecture someone
asked me whether I want to take the
Theta Infinity in the pattern you go
this is what we're supposed to do okay
well we'll see that first
um any question about this identity here
yes so where did the E not go I decided
it ends up because
upstairs and down here though
um okay so uh uh let's uh interpret
this top formula a bit uh because as I
said so far this is construction but we
can think of imagine that this is kind
of a time you'll lose your money imagine
your time if we draw a picture of
um colored talk
obviously
good
so uh I would say there's real time
and here's the minor nine
um
so um
we start with some State uh we're going
to evolve uh in Imagine time
uh by some amount
uh actually
the way I would like to uh
all right so this corresponds to uh the
evolution uh by minus i t which is
over here and I evolve down
um by the uh it's announced or minus i t
that corresponds to this emotion
operator and then I get to
uh after that Evolution I get to this
operator
it's already slot here
um and then I can rewrite this two hat
as uh the time evolution by T but thank
you hat then they evolve by minus
U on the right and Universe on the left
so um
so we can view that as uh
time Evolution uh in real estate uh by
some by the amount uh P here
um and uh and then I inserted
the operator two hands again
you have over here
um and then that operator there tells
you to uh evolve it after insert that
operator account state did that evolve
back in real time back to zero and then
this thing tells you to further evolve
uh provide some amounts by some large
amounts minus I2
okay so so this uh top expression can be
viewed as you have some operator
sandwich video size expect the value of
some operator what is this operator is
the time we losing the imaginary time
starting from here down this way for
some long imaginary time then go forward
in real time or insert a few hands go
for any real time is there another two
hats involve back in real time and then
uh down on the imagine the prime access
again
you can think of it that way
the green arrows are
these two highly Evolution numbers
so this is
just some picture to to a guy you're
thinking you don't find it that if
you're convenient to think of The
Spectator you can't ignore this picture
um now uh
alternatively
uh we could uh instead just consider uh
GLT for Imaginary time which actually
might be more convenient if you think in
terms of this picture so if
alternatively if you
know alternative
uh we can consider G just at P equals
minus one
positive real account
um so this this one as we said it's and
it's been the same expression you just
replace this that you have uh well the Q
hat p but if you had okay
foreign
possibility they've been released inside
e to the minus 1 over H bar Capital H
at P minus Tau T is very large because
it's going to be positive uh Q
0.
uh
[Music]
when I say divided sorry now we're going
to say
uh
okay so in this case uh you can we can
just speak of the evolution is imaginary
see uh where
um
uh three
starts with uh
wow let me just uh think of this uh tile
axis which is
the difference in the increasing
direction we will start as minus t
uh then we'll get to a Time Zero uh
where we'll research Q hat and then we
evolved by some
amount of time now
this Evolution operator and we insert
another two hats and then we evolve by T
minus
that's it
here
okay
um anyway so so this is just another way
to rewrite this two point function uh
with uh imaginary negative imagery
indeed uh and as I said uh this is
whatever where you write it the all
characters send me one information this
also captures the energy spectrum of uh
yeah
in a way that's describing over there so
for example if you know this function uh
and for a function Tau you can just do
the inverse buff transform and recover
the energy exactly
um so uh it's a widely bother
I think this
um
we're going to uh now investigate how to
access this observable using the
password
uh it will be convenient to work with uh
complementary time evolution in this
context of these recovery functions just
because as you'll see uh the path
integral is a better Behavior yes
so what critical information
the only intuition uh it's uh some uh
Matrix elements of operators there's no
uh at this point uh I don't need to give
any interpretation this is just
something I can study a capture the
energy spectrum and some other
information about metric settlement that
we still have
um the real reason that I'm gonna be
interested in this is because it's a
natural thing to cover using pattern
um uh so you know if you want to probe
any observable using pattern book this
is sort of the combinative thing to
start with but I haven't explained that
because apart from that there's no I
wouldn't assign any further physical
activity basis
any other questions
yeah
foreign
um okay so uh
so something happening well
how do we continue such a thing
well uh well here's a here's a nice
thing about it
um so in the past integral
but it only compute
this two-point assumption
um uh well uh you can follow
uh the same logic as the way we derive
The Matrix elemented operator last time
but it started doing a complete basis at
uh you know small steps of time
um and then you get rid of the conjugate
momentum well you know we did this dire
Mission about last time and it will
produce some kind of integration over uh
this path of Q uh going to some range of
time
um now what happens if you uh have this
additional insertion of Q hats uh well
uh you just uh you know
you know if you get to the point where
you have time zero you just insert the
screen half and then get time p is there
another two hats
um and if you calculate the Matrix
element of the student hat because this
p's and q's the end and Q and Laser
States uh you'll just pick up qn at that
step
so so the result of this uh and this
will be just calculated literally by
inserting a q t and q0 into the library
but no longer as operator but just as
variables and what I mean is this so you
would write integral DQ this measure
factor which we don't have to carefully
interpret this in value of computations
um we have t to the I over degrees power
and action a prior this would be from
convolutional time to some kind of time
or specify that in moment so lagrangian
I can give you that DT
um
and uh
uh well it's not same material Prime
um and uh this is going to insert QT
and uh zero
in here
um
now this is not quite the left hand side
yet because if you recall our generation
last time uh this pattern is about
within computes well first of all you
have to specify some boundary condition
uh now we do not want to specify
conditions of your final indeed we don't
have to specify because you know here
the side here is the arbitrary actually
I could have replayed this side by side
Prime this doesn't actually matter
um so so I can replay the five Prime by
Simon killing natural Side by some if
you find though it wouldn't have matters
uh that dependence will drop out
yes this if I if I evolve in this
specific way uh I'm only going to pick
up the contribution from the ground
state
um so uh and indeed that's the procedure
we're going to follow uh so if you take
this and divide by the passenger row
uh
the same path in the world but now
um
without this Q insertion
uh and then you take a limit
uh where you want to take essentially
the Imagine part of TF
okay so so this is going to be the
empathic representation of the uh to the
point correlation function of our
interest
um uh so far uh if I take tea to be
Realty uh and I follow this procedure
um then uh you know this
you have to interpret with action which
is
indeed you have to interpret that action
uh as a contour degree on a complexity
plane that follows exactly this path
I've drawn over there
uh things will be a little bit easier to
think about and more a little bit more
clear-cuts if I just declare that I want
to calculate the uh and the continued
version this quick rotated version of
the two-point query function uh Geo Tau
Ortiz
if I if I'm just interested in that uh
then
um I could uh uh just follow this path
uh just moving in imaginary time I don't
I don't have to do this weird thing over
there so that's a that's going to be a
bit more straightforward
uh any question about this formula here
yes just to make sure
so the q i and Q final can be any right
that's good that's correct so here I
don't even need to specify the boundary
condition because that depends on the
market will drop out in this limit
that that's why that's why I introduced
that that whole Gadget video
I mean I could have kept track of the
final condition but it's uh it'll make
things a little bit more Counting
okay uh any other questions
yeah so in this case we're taking
um like the states uh q0 timely runs it
equals the same QR
no no no no no no no uh no uh Qi uh
plays the role of this side primary and
the qf uh will play the row of the side
here and I don't have to specify them
because because the dependence on that
will drop out so so then how did we go
from what because
uh last time I never had this group had
research
so so last time uh so this is something
new compared to last time uh uh what you
had to do you can read me the the
derivation last time so uh you know for
example uh uh you see you can think of
this whole thing as I'm finding the
operator variable in this path in
complex time uh but at some point
actually because I mean
time you're gonna insert a few hacks
because
and then after some other time you got
to insert the list you have okay
uh that's the thing you want to
calculate right that's the thing on you
want to calculates when you call a
particular procedure what do you
actually do well you're gonna be
discretizing this steps
like we're doing it last time and those
two hats is going only going to enter in
that computation in this Matrix element
between you know the instruction of this
basis here and the basis is over there
uh but in that case uh you know if you
follow that derivation uh this Cube had
you know it's going to be done with some
q and P basis and it's interesting the Q
has on the cube base let's just pick up
this argument eigen value which is some
qn
this q and turns into Q
of t or Q of zero uh that is the now the
variable
of the integration so let me emphasize
no this is kind of a you know basically
but very important points which is that
on the left-hand side this is an
operator
so so then I have this operator
and this corresponds to the instruction
of this effect so I'm I'm you know here
I'm integrating over the space of
functions Q of P or any t uh so the Q 0
is one of these simply many variables if
you wish and the skill T is another
point of this
variables uh and I just insert that into
the integral this is part of the
integrand
and the claim is that this pattern it
was supposed to reproduce that that
answer provided that you regularize this
measure correctly as we expand it
said
imaginary
it all throughout
uh so that's not literally like I will
do that in a moment but I said so far
I'm still in this way of writing I'm
still taking the key to be real and then
in order to do that I have to interpret
this action as defined by following this
path over here
I guess that that's the reason I I do
this
through the start here right so I have
to follow this this entire time
okay uh but uh certainly I'm going to
say that if I instead of the work with
them during the imaginary tea I just had
to drive this red Point down here then I
just go down this way don't have to
worry about this which is why it's
convenient to work with g at the
negative imagery
uh yes but the whole point is that
acceleration is unambiguous if you have
if you know the function for imagery
yeah
it is analytic on this lower half
complexity plane then that has all the
information to determine the function
and reality
because
uh I'm not sure what do you mean by can
do analytic I mean the function is
you know when we prove there and see
calculus for a reason
oh uh uh uh well uh I didn't say uh
ideas that I haven't been doing this in
March with me uh but uh we can launch
into a lengthy discussion of how you
numerically and continue that's actually
a very interesting subject but it will
take us a bit uh far from from the theme
but
um
but numerically you can help me also do
that you see this this procedure of uh
repeated headers here this is not a
multiplication way calculation but it is
anyway if you go if I go to Archer if I
order in the Taylor series on this you
can this is not just some imagination of
mathematicians this you can do on the
computer
okay uh any uh other questions
okay
um
um so uh let's see
um okay so um uh so now uh as I as I
have reloaded to uh I don't want to keep
talking about this we are a contour here
so it's a little bit more convenient if
I just work with a negative imagery T so
we're going to from now uh often uh
consider this rotation
um so we're gonna take UNT and take uh P
to be minus signed out very often often
uh when there's no room for confusion
I'm still going to write this as Q of
Tau uh but it's understood that the
Qatar is actually a different function
right it's an integration of this two at
least now
it's really cute minus ital but you know
probably will be clear depending on the
context what I actually need
yeah I could have maybe put like like
this but let me know
um
okay so this is by a slide uh notation
um and uh if I if I so uh now if I apply
that to uh this actually on the
lagrangian I would kind of derivative of
q a q dot P by DT of Q so that will
become uh
foreign
so
uh so typically
for example this uh La Grande so I
suppose this lagrangea is in the form
let's say it's religion actually
potential magnetic term is a potential
term right uh and if I do this
replacement it goes to a minus I doubt
uh I would write this as I will replace
these two dots with I times C by the
time of Q so this becomes minus one half
foreign
and of course if I integrate also this
measure DT has to be become has to be
replaced by minus I uh
um and um
um so
um e to the I over H bar integral L of u
q Dot
and they did under this weak rotation
and
it will become well what does it become
well this T is going to become uh uh
minus I DP is going to become minus I
detailed but I'm going to write such as
this minus I and I where it's okay so
but I'm going to put the extra minus 9
in front and Define this thing in here
as the what we usually call the
euclidean version of lagrangian the wick
rotating version is a function of Q and
Tau of Q where my convention is always
going to be such that this l q q dot is
it defined to be minus well euclidean uh
Q has been held Q so for example uh if l
here the usual lagrangian is one half q
dot squared minus V of Q then this
euclidean version of lagrangian
is just uh
it's minus of that so now it becomes
plus one half d by d p q square plus a d
over
okay so the reason for this assignment
is just that I want to make this L
euclidean
um this guy here I want this to be
positive uh so the potential is the
boundary from below so this thing is a
function as a functional well as
function of Q
this Foundation below
okay so so in this uh which rotation
procedure uh replacing T by minus I Tau
and this exponential here this waiting
factor in the pack really well that
becomes uh e to the minus one over H bar
the integral of the what I call the
euclidean lagrangian l e uh
um and as I said typically this guy here
is going to be uh positive or boundary
From Below and so
um unlike uh This original when you're
back in patio which is uh you know for
the real path this will be some phase
which is oscillatory you you might
imagine that that's kind of uh let's say
numerically important to calculate
because you have this while the acid is
is
that then converts to my question
um but uh once you do this quick
rotation it looks much better because
now this guy here is going to be
exponentially suppressed for wildly
fluctuating pads so it's going to be
dominated by the kind of hat that really
have a small values of the euclidean
action which is the quantity that's
bounded From Below
okay so so that's another reason uh why
this uh which related version of the
planet is much nicer to work with
because uh it actually will have a much
better conversion property
uh any questions so far
like minus like if it's the magnets like
you just uh so the side here is
important uh I have to find the sign of
the canister right so this L is minus l
e and this one is icons are getting the
I so the sign is correct
euclidean action
it differs from the usual connection of
the action Better Sound
I don't listen
all right so um
so with that uh
we understand that if you want to
calculate this
uh
you you play a version related version
of this two-point function uh we can
just use the nuclear version which is uh
um you know well you just replace that
way back by this and uh and this
integration range is going to be found
like minus T2
minus t into the T if you wish then they
take limit this particularly to Infinity
about in the numerator
and the result is supposed to be well
defined that gives you the actual uh and
regulation two-point functions
okay
um
any questions yeah
so in general we're going to perform a
work rotation we get you know some path
integral which is a lot lifestablization
right but in order to get back to our
actual measurable cervical right we have
to find you know what that analytic
situation equals uh well uh you can uh
so you know you know I mean this
intuition you know you can extract this
identity levels without having to
explicit within information in fact it's
you know in the sense actually easier
but this is what people
you know I actually do in uh
we'll not get to that anytime soon but
uh you know
this is uh not just uh uh you know
um uh some uh abstract mathematics uh it
can be turned into academical
computations of actual energy levels for
example uh let me
yes
um but but uh in uh both you know this
kind of simple model but also later in
actual uh vulnerable Theory
um uh these kind of quality functions
are expected to be uh have a nice energy
property that's expected
um provided that I'm not important
filtering is actually defined it's
actually well defined so so in a
non-portrait defined Financial Theory
such as Quantum Yuma theory important
Dimension or 5433 Dimension
um these kind of functions are going to
be well defined uh uh for things like
QED it will not quite be well defined
but that's because QD itself is not
defined a number of different level it's
only defined level of predivision theory
so in that case there are various
pathologies associated with this kind of
coordinary function
any other questions
yes
um what if the two operators
ah uh ideas uh okay good uh so uh so far
uh you see um this is uh uh you don't
get to choose the water okay so so the
water is specified
um uh so far
alternated here
um I'm always going to be uh uh in a
specific ordering
um uh in fact for this euclidean uh
version uh of the uh
so you know if you if you switch uh q0
and Q on one side now
um You Might uh be in trouble because
that's like negative uh negative tell
and I I don't know that in this
entrepreneur
I don't know that
um so uh uh
uh what we'll discuss later uh how to uh
uh starts with this kind of a quick
rotation of the ukulele American query
function and recover the uh the the
real-time moments about the region but
it's so far you know this is not a Write
the basic Theory so the renting will be
somewhere but uh we will later
understand how to recover uh query
functions with arbitrary ordering but
for now the the order is as expected
any other questions
invest in a part of the variation step
by step and you don't get you don't get
your troops
in this case it's always spotters
um all right uh so uh next we're going
to discuss how to actually evaluate the
pathway well we're writing this after
expression but uh are we just pulling
ourselves or does this actually they're
actually useful for computation well of
course you can always go back to this a
realized version like last lecture but
we just do that and then uh We're Not
Really Gonna gain anything because you
just go back to the Panasonic
formulation we somehow like to do a
little better than that
um so but the key here is actually going
to be that
um you know once you we decided that
this integration is supposed to be
integration over path of pill in time or
in people in time or imagine time
um there are different ways to
parametrize the space or functions of P
like last time we tried to the project
very function it just by discretizing
time and and every time we have one
variable but they are better things you
can do for example you can Fourier
transform in time you might consider uh
expanding to take a thing you might you
might consider the Fourier expansion of
Q of T so instead of working Queue at a
longer time you go to frequency space or
a transform and then you instead of
integration queue but every time you
integrate over the Fourier modes of uh
every uh frequency okay so that turned
out to be much more convenient for
private computations and we'll discuss
one example of that and it also is for
another example before
and in fact this way of thinking about
the path signal as the integration of
the Fourier notes is much more
convenient for doing what we'll see that
doing preservation Theory
foreign
so to evaluate
uh
the not really girl
uh well the key
uh will be
to
find
a convenient
and also uh regularized
expression
of the measure let's DQ
okay so for example uh as I said I would
like to potentially work in uh some kind
of a frequency space so you can imagine
taking cure a towel
um you can expand this on some video
bases or functions of how so some more
and some q and F and Tau and this F in
the pal
is going to be some uh suitable
uh basis of the functions between now
uh you know they could be you know
employer mode so it could be something
else
um and uh the uh naive realities you
might imagine that you can replace this
integration in the function field of
Health by the integration in the
conditions which are really the only
weird about this
functions if these are exposure
functions say this uh then uh deployment
modes and uh overhand
ability
now of course this will still be
International integral but you might
imagine uh not getting this on a large
group
okay so that's something that one might
attempt to do
any questions
uh well that is this question mark here
uh you don't know that
[Music]
by this gaussian
all right so so that will become
contributed to this measure now in some
people situation this will actually be
true after some constant normalization
you think your nine space is the
function at best but that may not always
be the case
um
uh this will come back to Pilot a little
bit uh well we'll see that in one
mechanics uh but it turns out that uh
the recently which uh things are nicer
if you want to build
uh
uh and this reason it really had to do
with the Retro visiting locality so as I
emphasize in the first lecture opponent
filter is a specializer in quantum
mechanics it's a nice version of quantum
mechanics where some ambiguities don't
actually gets resolved by the
requirement of locality
but uh these words probably does not
mean much right now but uh so uh let me
postpone the proper answer to that
question
but uh but in fact the problem too in
the promise uh is uh precisely uh asking
you going to reacting to study this uh
in a very simple one problem
example of a quantity mechanics
yes
integrals converges to something and
that is uh you should say that
yeah so um
uh let's do this for the simplest uh
example of uh
one of the simplest examples of one
mechanical models
with the increasing level of
sophistication okay so we're gonna first
discuss the harmonic acid
um okay so
example one
is just the harmonic the quantum
harmonic with the quantum harmonic
oscillator uh so the hamiltonian is as
you know uh p squared plus Omega squared
two hat squared uh over two I'm studying
the word last one
um and then uh this of course at the
classical level uh will correspond to uh
a lagrangian that is just one half q dot
squared minus the potential we just
won't have omega squared
Q squared
um okay and uh uh we are going to uh
investigate
um
this uh kind of a two point for your
function of Interest
now a verse uh actually you know from
the undergrad hungry but what is the
ground state and the Waypoint
representation if you wish and Q is just
a position operator in that case uh and
you just calculate this explicit but
we're going to go through this painful
process using Pat people to calculate it
so
um and to do that
um uh we're going to consider the quick
rotating version
so uh we're starting with the our
original happy one I keep my mind and we
have described and we're going to be
calculating things like integral and DQ
of e to the minus one of H bar do you
put it in action with some insertion
into this excuse before if you're
interested in uh two point foreign
thank you
um so in fact I want to do this example
as explicitly impossible and so we're
actually going to
um choose uh boundary condition so so
we're going to take this uh action to be
uh the integral of this equilibrium
version of lagrangian uh from some say
minus P to T that's like I mentioned
I've been using implicitly earlier
um so uh as I said the boundary industry
is not going to actually matter in the
line T to Infinity uh but it will be a
step for now just to show you the
explicit computation I'm going to start
by taking a PW finite and actually do
this uh in the this functional
integration so to do that we do want to
in order to you know have a definite
computation we like to choose some
binary condition so we're going to
choose
uh the boundary condition
and
imaginary time
so or with Q L remember this now is
rotated it's a matter of time
um so true there can be such that Q of
minus t is equal to zero and the Q of T
is also zero
okay so in other words
now we're evolving and you plan time
from minus 16 to 8 and uh so
some object function does
that okay sorry zero and start by zero
um so uh given uh this constraint we can
expand a general function uh on the
four-year basis subject to this next
frame that's what they expand
uh
uh if you're now on the foyer basis in
this case because of the boundary
condition
um
over q and f n l and from one to
Infinity what are this Advanced well you
can choose this at ends
to be uh
proportional to the sign of n i uh Tau
plus p over 3T
and so forth so uh this is a complete
basis of uh functions uh the advantage
book that titles minus t
hope you can
distinguish my handwriting this is two
which is not to be confused with now uh
in this Tau so tell plus d we have
disadvantages that minus how would minus
d
know this is a complete basis
um but uh it will be uh
useful to normalize this I'm gonna stick
it in one of our square root T factor
and just to normalize this function at
an end
um so far is a bit ad hoc but uh I'm not
gonna be uh
for them so
let me tell you this a bit more
precisely
so uh
yeah that's how
um uh is uh
basis
functions
uh that today
uh the
prescribed the boundary condition
I'm Hungary
condition
uh and uh orthonormal
for for the normal
uh with respect to
a Super Bowl it defines inner products
functions
for example
that is to say that we're going to be an
inner part between the X
to be
integral from 90 state to T
and star of the family
and this should be move on demand that
this is
say that is autonomous way back to this
inner product defined by different way
um
any questions about this
so I'm just expanding uh this is the
point expansion so in terms of in terms
of this uh we can then write this
include an action so what's the equation
in this example the integral from minus
P to T
one half you can tell a few squared plus
one half
Omega squared Q squared comes out right
so remember so uh go if you go through
them we go through your procedure and
flip the overall sign this is our
euclidean lebronian
uh now you take that extension and plug
it into
here and it can re-extend this action uh
in terms of
uh the QX
so in terms of the Cubans
um what is the
action well um
it's uh
um
all the time so let me just quickly uh
state to this and uh and I'll finish uh
this next time so uh it is very
important company you just said let me
pick this and plug it into the integral
uh
um you'll find that uh
you know so so you take this and the
stick into this entire queue and
multiply by another project without
queue uh I just have q n times qm
during the FN uh but that integral you
can do and you'll find out that the
result is going to be non-zero only if n
is equal to M and the result of this and
this and sum over and uh
uh q and squared uh one half and I over
and c 200 plus one have omega squared so
um the first term come from the
beginning
uh the second term comes from this
well thank you this is
and that's the result of that then
action as a function of qns
right so um this happy to grow
uh whatever it is that you want
something to start which you can study
and we will study next time when I
insert like some cues and from that
we'll extract this quantity function uh
so that uh we're gonna compute by uh
turning it into the course integration
over this poem about qn so the product
and from one to Infinity uh and uh this
action is just minus one over H bar sum
Over N from y to Infinity uh one half of
uh M pi over two t squared plus Omega
uh
two N squared and with whatever QA
searches uh that you want to put in
uh now this integral you all know how to
do at least one by one it's just a
gaussian integral because I've chosen
this unprinted approaches quite really
you can see that the kinetic term is a
diagonal so there's no mixing of between
the Q and the qm or different n and n
gaussian integrals uh but we're going to
be interested in insertion of additional
cues
uh and unfortunately I don't have time
now I will finish that calculation
um
uh
next time yes so let's give this away
because we can follow each
um
that's correct that's correct so far uh
this is the Ukrainian government now you
see uh uh yeah that's correct
uh if you you might imagine that
um
you know if you
um you're going to do this in a lot in
time you might you might worry that uh
you know instead of expanding Factor you
have some positive base but actually
um we've set up the the you know the
real-time competition such a way that
it's actually still going to look more
nice like like this because you had a
problem that that weird time come to
work where most of it is still in
imaginary time Direction so ultimately
in in a sense that this kind of a path
in the world in one mechanics is always
should always be viewed as defines
really imaginary time that that's that's
the best way to think about it it is the
um
it's sort of the path people that this
uh mathematically
yes
uh good so uh first of all a first
comment is that
um you could of course imagine training
online attention here's normalization
measure but that's on constant if you
change by some constant I I wouldn't
worry about it because ultimately uh I
don't care about over organization on
this it's going to cancel between the
numerator and Dynamics if I'm interested
in the important functions
uh you might worry about uh
um the dependence
it depends on okay in some way and that
could be bad
uh
um that now did not happen in this
example uh you will uh that the purpose
of a problem Set uh the problem two in
in the in the problem set I have was
just posted is precisely to let you
study uh this to investigate this
nomination in a in a similar but
actually even simpler than this in some
sense example uh and uh well you see uh
if you use that this will be time
regularization as we have the right last
time you know what noise is supposed to
do because when we derived from Hamilton
so in that case there's no ambiguity
um in this case while we don't know what
the matter is but if you in first of all
you know uh going from this q and to
those Q so this qn or the poem The Last
Time those are at least we apply to the
different variables
factor is
okay so you could study that and you can
figure out what it is
um uh I'm not going to discuss that
right now in fact uh that uh Jacobian
Factor even was a remark at the end of
the P set it's an extra credit part of
them it's not you're not even required
to study that you're coping Factor well
it's really some aspects of
personalization you'll see that it's not
always trivial sometimes you have to
keep track
um but in this example it turns out that
it's not there's no there's no uh actual
uh non-trivial uh dependence uh
yes
uh well the limits are commands me to
put it you're integrating over all
possible functions here uh so I'm sorry
I mean these four amounts are under
strength uh in this case real errors
is
yeah
um uh that depends on uh what what you
what you want to get get out of it uh
you know you could say that uh there's
regularization I did last time is a way
to make it rigorous uh but it may not
preserve all the problems you want to
preserve listen to their life
Enlightenment that we've been talking
about is that like a well-defined like
nightmare space on the space of the past
uh on the actual space the functions
that depends I believe a simple cases at
least in the gaussian case if it
actually can be made like a rigorous on
the space of functions uh but uh
um this is not something I will get into
uh in this class
um uh in practice uh and that is almost
never used in physics but it's something
that is worth understanding impossible
and uh
I think uh
applications but for these are very
simple models it can be made precise
but but for our purpose we're always
going to think about this um as defined
through regularization we're not going
to try to you know consider some uh you
know measure on some organizations
facing functions
um
uh any other questions